Guide to the Abram Kanof Papers, 1858-1996 RL.00766
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Abram Kanof papers
1858-1996 and undated
1928-1991
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kanof, Abram, 1903-
RL.00766
17.7 Linear Feet
circa 8,500
Access
Part of the Writings Series in this collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Abram Kanof Papers were donated to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 1979 to 2017.
Biographical Note
Missing Title
1903, Dec. 25 Born, Russia
1924 Graduated from Columbia University
1928 Received M.D. from the State University of New York Medical School
1931 Married Frances Pascher
1948-1962 Chairman, Jewish Museum, New York, N.Y.
1956 Founded the Tobe Pascher Workshop, Jewish Museum, New York, N.Y.
1961-1964 President, American Jewish Historical Society
1965-1972 Professor of Pediatrics, State University of New York Downstate Medical Center
1970 Published Jewish Ceremonial Art and Religious Observance
1971 Received the Maimonides Award for Service to Medicine and Judaism.
1972- Emeritus Professor of Pediatrics, State University of New York Downstate Medical Center
ca.1975-1980 Guest Curator of Judaica, North Carolina Museum of Art, Raleigh, N.C.
1999 Died
Collection Overview
The Abram Kanof Papers, 1858-1996, contain printed material, correspondence, writings, and photographs primarily reflecting Dr. Kanof's research and writing in the field of Jewish ceremonial art; his role in the development of the Tobe Pascher Workshop of the Jewish Museum, New York, N.Y.; his curatorship at the North Carolina Museum of Art, Raleigh, N.C.; and to a lesser extent, his patronage of the arts. The Abram Kanof Papers are relevant to the study of religious art in the Judaic tradition, and they also document Dr. Kanof's contributions, as a researcher, patron, and administrator, to the study of the relationship between art and Jewish liturgy and worship.
A substantial part of the collection consists of printed material, including exhibition programs, handbills, articles, journals, and clippings, which is contained in the Subject Files Series. Information pertaining to topics within this series includes art and religion; symbolism; synagogue architecture and decoration; the American Jewish Historical Society; Jewish ceremonial art; liturgical or ritual objects; and artists, including Ludwig Wolpert and Moshe Zabari, both resident artists of the Tobe Pascher Workshop. Primary materials relevant to the history, administration, and programs of the Jewish Museum as well as the development of the Tobe Pascher Workshop are contained in the Subject Files Series. The Correspondence Series primarily reflects Dr. Kanof's role in the formation of the workshop, which was developed to provide for the creation of art and liturgical objects to be used in synagogues as well as serve as an instructional center for training artists.
Pictures of items from exhibitions held at the Jewish Museum and the North Carolina Museum of Art as well as images used in Kanof's Jewish Ceremonial Art and Religious Observance are contained in the Pictures Series. Typescripts, page proofs and galley proofs for Dr. Kanof's works, and offprints and drafts of some of his other writings are contained in the Writings Series.
Selected publications from the Abram Kanof Papers have been cataloged for the rare book collection of the Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Synagogue architecture; Synagogue art; Judaism and art; Judaism -- Liturgical objects; Judaism -- Liturgical objects -- Exhibitions; Handbills; Jewish art and symbolism; Art, Jewish; Ceremonial objects; Art, Jewish -- Exhibitions; Art, Jewish -- Catalogs; Art museums -- United States; Art and religion; Symbolism; Art patronage -- United States; Zabari, Moshe, 1935-; Jewish Museum (New York, N. Y.) -- Tobe Pascher Workshop; Kanof, Abram, 1903-. Jewish ceremonial art and religious observance; Jewish Museum (New York, N.Y.); Kanof, Abram, 1903-. Jewish symbolic art; Wolpert, Ludwig Y. (Ludwig Yehuda), 1900-1981; North Carolina Museum of Art
- Subject Files, 1858-1996, undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Primarily contains printed material, including clippings, programs, newsletters, handbills, exhibit programs, journals, and journal articles. Also included are typed copies of articles, memoranda, and minutes. The files reflect Dr. Kanof's research interests in Jewish ceremonial art as well as other subject areas in the field of art; a substantial number of the files pertain to the administration and programs of the Jewish Museum and Judaic art exhibits at the North Carolina Museum of Art. Arranged alphabetically by subject and chronologically by year within the folders.
  - The Abram and Frances Kanof Collection of Ceremonial Objects, 1961-1965, undated (Box 1)
  - The Akedah in art, 1922-1969, undated (Box 1)
  - American Jewish Historical Society, 1965-1981 (Box 1)
  - Archaeology, 1903-1977, undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Art and Religion, 1914-1986, undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Art, Contemporary Jewish, 1936-1971, undated (Box 1)
  - Art galleries, 1954-1974, undated (Box 1)
  - Art, God, Man, 1928-1984, undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Art history, Jewish, 1926-1981, undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Artists:
    - A-C, 1946-1991, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Chagall, Marc, 1930-1972, undated (Box 1)
    - D-E, 1968-1980 (Box 1)
    - F-L, 1928-1991, undated, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - M-R, 1954-1987, undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - S-Z, 1923-1986, undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Richard, Chava Wolpert, 1970-1990, undated (Box 2)
    - Zabari, Moshe, 1986 (Box 11)
    - General, 1925-1983, undated, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Arts and crafts, 1923-1978, undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Awards, 1954, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Background research, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Background research and bibliographies, undated (Box 2)
  - Berenson, Bernard, 1949, 1966 (Box 2)
  - The Bezalel, 1962-1975 (Box 2)
  - Biblical themes, 1931-1985, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Books and book collections, Jewish, 1940-1988, undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Books and manuscripts, 1928-1991, undated (Box 2)
  - Calendars, 1940-1959, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Calendars, 1959-1996, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Ceremonial art, Jewish, 1958-1990, undated (Box 3)
  - Ceremonial objects:
    - 1961-1987, undated (Box 3)
    - Literature on, 1886-1971, undated (Box 3)
  - Ceremony, psychological basis of, 1958, undated (Box 3)
  - Coins and tokens, 1858-1969, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Dura Europos, 1937-1965, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Eastern European Jewish communities, 1969, 1988, undated (Box 3)
  - The Educational Alliance, 1919-1965 (Box 3)
  - Exhibits:
    - 1935-1990, undated (Box 3)
    - Multiple artists, 1956-1988 (Box 3)
  - Folk art, 1905-1990, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Hanukkah, 1950-1988 (Box 3)
  - The Hebrew alphabet, 1960-1989, undated (Box 3)
  - Hellenism, 1890-1974, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Holocaust, 1965-1990, undated (Box 3)
  - Honoring R. Schoen, undated (Box 3)
  - Islamic art, 1967-1975, undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Israeli art, 1962-1986, undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Israeli artists: A-W, 1962-1985, undated (Box 4)
  - Jewish art, literature on, 1925-1989, undated, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Jewish Ceremonial Art and Religious Observance, reviews, etc., 1970-1979, undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - The Jewish Museum:
    - Administration and Policy, 1950-1988, undated, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Blueprints, 1962, 1976, undated (Box 4)
    - Exhibits, 1949-1988, undated (Box 4)
    - History, 1945-1992, undated, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Programming, 1948-1991, undated, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Jewish Museum, 1939-1984, undated, 8 folders (Box 5)
  - Judaism and art, 1936-1982, undated, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Kanof oral history, 1992-1993 (Box 5)
  - Ketubah, 1969, 1975, undated (Box 5)
  - Lectures, 1970-1984, undated (Box 5)
  - Manuscripts, ancient and illuminated, 1928, 1978, undated (Box 5)
  - The Menorah, 1903-1979, undated, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Museums/Exhibits, 1948-1991, undated, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - National Museum of American Jewish History, 1965-1985 (Box 5)
  - North Carolina Museum of Art, 1974-1991, undated, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Painters, 1925-1987, undated, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Passover, 1940-1978, undated, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Pucker/Safrai Gallery, 1971-1990, undated (Box 6)
  - Rituals and ceremonies, 1947-1969 (Box 6)
  - Sculptors: E-Z 1928-1969, undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Sculptors: Wolpert, Ludwig, 1975-1995, undated (Box 11)
  - Shield of David, 1949, undated (Box 6)
  - Symbolism, 1946-1987, undated, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Synagogues:
    - American, 1956-1977, undated (Box 6)
    - Ancient/Antique, 1915-1991, undated, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Architecture:
      - Modern, 1925-1977, undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Wooden, 1925-1981, undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Synagogues: Dedications and services, 1950-1977, undated (Box 6)
  - Temple vessels, 1981 (Box 6)
  - Tombs, burial objects, and burial rites, 1964-1978, undated (Box 6)
  - Torah orientation, 1934-1978, undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Visual arts and material culture, 1963, 1966, undated (Box 6)
  - Wolpert, Ludwig, 1958-1991, undated, 4 folders (Box 7)
- Pictures, 1932-1979, undated
  Chiefly consists of black and white photographs of artworks displayed in exhibits held by the North Carolina Museum of Art and the Jewish Museum as well as works created by particular artists. Some of the folders, such as those pertaining to Ludwig Wolpert and synagogues, have counterparts in the Subject Files Series. Arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically by year within the folders. Miscellaneous photographs are arranged chronologically by year and follow the pictures which are topically arranged.
  - Archaeology, undated (Box 7)
  - Arts and crafts, 1968, undated (Box 7)
  - Barmitzvah, circumcision, marriage, memorial, 1956-1969, undated (Box 7)
  - Bernstein, Rabinowitz and Richard, 1972-1978, undated (Box 7)
  - Ceremonial art, Jewish, undated, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Collections pictures, undated (Box 7)
  - Fabrics, 1958, 1974, undated (Box 7)
  - Jewish museum: Exhibition Commemorating 300th Anniversary of Jewish Settlement in the United States, 1954, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Modern ceremonial objects, undated (Box 7)
  - North Carolina Museum of Art exhibit, 1991 (Box 7)
  - North Carolina Museum of Art:
    - Ceremonial Art in the Judaic Tradition, 1953-1976, undated, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Ceremonial Art in the Judaic Tradition, exhibit: General layout, 1975 (Box 7)
    - Judaic Art Exhibit, 1975 (Box 7)
    - Judaica Gallery: Objects, undated, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Moshe Kupferman, 1991 (Box 7)
    - Permanent Judaica collection, undated, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous photos, undated (Box 7)
  - Seder plates, undated (Box 7)
  - Symbolic art. Jewish, undated, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Synagogues: Ancient/Antique, undated (Box 7)
  - Synagogue art and arks: (Box 8)
    - 1958-1962, undated (Box 8)
    - Miller, Leon G., undated (Box 8)
    - Horn, Milton, 1974, undated (Box 8)
  - Torah pointers, 1974, undated (Box 8)
  - Tubi, Shalom, 1974-1979, undated (Box 8)
  - Wolpert, Ludwig, 1962, undated (Box 8)
  - Zabari, Moshe, undated (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1932-1979, undated, 9 folders (Box 8)
- Writings, 1949-1993, undated
  Included are typescripts, galley proofs and page proofs for Kanof's Jewish Ceremonial Art and Religious Observance as well as offprints and drafts pertaining to art and medicine by Kanof. Primarily arranged alphabetically by author. Also included are autographed writings given to Dr. Kanof by other others. The typescript of Jewish Ceremonial Art and Religious Observance has been arranged according to the order of its chapters.
  - [Artists and the Holocaust], undated (Box 8)
  - Davidowitz, Moshe, The Menorah, 1971 (Box 8)
  - Encyclopedia of Jewish-American History and Culture entry, 1987-1988, undated, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Kanof:
    - Jewish Ceremonial Art and Religious Observance:
      - Ceremony and Art in Jewish Life (typescripts), undated (Box 8)
      - Judaism and Art (typescripts), undated (Box 8)
      - Form and Style in Jewish Ceremonial Art (typescript), undated (Box 8)
      - Motifs and Symbols in Jewish Ceremonial Art (typescripts), undated (Box 8)
      - Light in Jewish Ceremonial Art (typescripts), undated (Box 8)
      - Wine in Jewish Ceremonial Art (typescripts), undated (Box 8)
      - The Sabbath: Light, Wine, and Spice (typescripts), undated (Box 8)
      - Passover and the Seder (typescripts), undated (Box 8)
      - Sukkot, Hanukkah, Purim (typescript), undated (Box 8)
      - Ceremonial Markers in the Jewish Life Cycle (typescripts), undated (Box 8)
      - Hallmarks of Jewish Home (typescripts), undated (Box 8)
      - The Synagogue: Evolution, Architecture, and contents (typescripts), undated (Box 8)
      - Jews and Art (typescript), undated (Box 8)
      - Acknowledgements and lists of photographs (typescripts), undated (Box 8)
    - Page proofs, pp. 1-159, undated, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Galley proofs, undated (Box 8)
    - Jewish Symbolic Art:
      - Page proofs, undated, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous writings, 1953-1993, undated (Box 9)
  - Schoenberger, Guido: Drafts and typescripts, 1949-1970, undated, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Sermonettes, 1984-1986, undated (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1949-1984, undated (Box 9)
- Correspondence, 1953-1991.
  Primarily includes letters and memoranda documenting the creation and administration of the Tobe Pascher Workshop of the Jewish Museum. To a lesser extent, letters pertaining to broader administrative concerns of the Jewsih Museum are included. Dr. Kanof's direction in the development of the Tobe Pascher Workshop as well as the financial support he and Mrs. Kanof provided for the workshop is reflected in this series. See the folders under Jewish Museum in the Subject Files Series for related materials. Also contains materials pertaining to the Abram and Frances Pascher Kanof Collection of Jewish Art, Archaeology and Symbolism held in the Rubenstein Library at Duke University. Correspondents include Arthur Katz, Ludwig Wolpert and Abram Kanof. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1953-1991, undated, 5 folders (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous, 1931-1996, undated.
  Printed material, including postcards, clippings, programs, pertaining to Judaism and art, and publications on aspects of Jewish art history. Also contains four pieces of artwork.
  - Articles, 1970-1992, undated (Box 11)
  - Artwork, undated, 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Catalogs, 1972, undated (Box 11)
  - Duke University, 1987-1992, undated (Box 9)
  - Marriage certificate, 1974 (Oversize-folder 3)
  - North Carolina Museum of Art, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Notiz blatt der Gesellschaft zur Erforschung jüdischer Kunstdenkmäler: (Box 9)
    - 1902-1933, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - 1910-1996, undated, 6 folders (Box 9)
- Oversize Materials
  - Subject Files, 1919-1991 (Box 10)
  - Subject Files, 1946-1991, undated
    - Archaeology-Synagogues Dedication and Services, 1946-1991 and undated (Oversize-folder 1)
    - The Jewish Museum: Blueprints, 1962, 1976 and undated (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1959-1991, undated (Box 10)
  - Writings, 1971-1990 (Box 10)